Guide to the Women in the Visual and Literary Arts Records
University of Houston Libraries
Women in the Visual and Literary Arts Records
1994-2011
1994-2000
1999-002
Women in the Visual and Literary Arts
6.50 Linear Feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
The papers of the Women in Visual and Literary Arts (WIVLA) consist of meeting minutes, fliers about events, and newsletters. All material dates from 1994 to 2011.
Historical Note:
The Women in Visual and Literary Arts (WIVLA) attempts to combine the talent of visual artists and writers in order to stimulate the creative process and provide a forum for female artistic endeavors through shows and networking. The organization began in 1993, the brainchild of "a writer, an artist, an art consultant and a gallery owner." Within a year, membership flourished quickly. The organization holds monthly meetings that include a featured speaker, and also holds exhibits and readings where members may present their latest work. In the future, WIVLA hopes to provide "studios, writing suites, workshop space, gallery, gift shop and library" in order to facilitate the flowering of artistic activity among the women of Houston.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
Women in the Visual and Literary Arts
Genre/Form of Material:
Administrative records; Bylaws (administrative records); Correspondence; Minutes; Newsletters; Photographs
Topical Term:
Art -- Texas -- Houston; Art and literature -- Texas -- Houston; Artists -- Texas -- Houston; Arts -- Texas -- Houston; Women artists -- Texas -- Houston
Acquisition Information:
Donated by Women in the Visual and Literary Arts, 1999. Additional materials were acquired in 2010 as part of a donation by Women in the Visual and Literary Arts.
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
All meeting minutes and treasury reports are closed for three years.
Related Materials:
Houston Gorilla Girls Records http://archon.lib.uh.edu/index.php?p=collections/controlcard&id=468
Scope and Contents
The papers of the Women in Visual and Literary Arts (WIVLA) consist of meeting minutes, fliers about events, and newsletters. All material dates from 1994 to 2011. The collection arrived in the archives in excellent order, arranged neatly into newsletters and meeting minutes, which were filed and arranged chronologically. The collection has been broken into five series: Administration, Publications, Events, Multi-Media, and Various Materials.
Detailed List of Contents
- Administration
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of materials related to the administration of the organization. Included are materials related to the history and governance, finances, and membership of WIVLA. The sub-series related to the Board of Directors includes both meeting minutes as well as information on Board Retreats. For photograph materials related to meetings and retreats refer to Series 4. All meeting minutes and treasury reports are not to be photocopied at any time.
  - Organization
    - Bylaws, 1995, 1998, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Database, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - General Information, 1994-2000 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Guidelines, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Officer Descriptions, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Scholarships, 2001, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Storage, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Storage, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Surveys, 1996-2003 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Website, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Committees
    - Mailing Committee, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Nominating Committee, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Performance Committee, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Publicity and Marketing Committee, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Underwriter Committee, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Financial
    - Treasurer’s Reports, 1994-1996 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Treasurer’s Reports, 1997-1999 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Treasurer’s Reports, 2000-2006 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Membership
    - Correspondence, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Directory, 2000-2001 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Directory, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Directory, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Directory, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Directory, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Directory, 2010-2011 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Lists, 1994-1998 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Lists, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - New Members, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - New Members, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - New Members, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - New Members, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - New Members, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - New Members, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - New Members, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Non-Renewals, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Officials, 1994-2003 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Past Presidents, undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Renewals, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Renewals, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Renewals, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Renewals, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Renewals, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Renewals, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Renewals, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Roster-Charter Members, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Roster, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Roster, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Roster, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Roster, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Roster, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Roster, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Roster, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Roster, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Roster, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Various, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence
    - Events, 1997-2001 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Fundraisers and Donations, 1997-2005 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Organization, 1994-2001 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Speakers, 1998-1999 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Various, 1995-2011 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Board of Directors
    - General Information, 1994-2006 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Meeting Ideas, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Meeting, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Meeting, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Meeting, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Meeting, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Meeting, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Meeting, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Meeting, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Meeting, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Meeting, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Meeting, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Meeting, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Meeting, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Meeting, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Meeting, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Meeting, 2010 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Meeting, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Retreat, April 24-25, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Retreat, May 21-23, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Retreat, May 2000 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Retreat, May 4, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Retreat, April 2003 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Retreat, May 1, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Retreat, May 21, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Retreat, April 2007 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Retreat, May 23, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Retreat, May 15, 2010 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Retreat, 2012 (Box 2, Folder 45)
- Publications
  This series consists of publications released by WIVLA including newsletters and anthologies. The newsletters contain information about the organization and events WIVLA was involved. The anthologies are printed collections of members’ works including poems, stories and artwork.
  - Newsletters, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Newsletters, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Newsletters, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Newsletters, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Newsletters, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Newsletters, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Newsletters, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Newsletters, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Newsletters, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Newsletters, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Newsletters, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Newsletters, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Newsletters, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Newsletters, 2010 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Newsletters, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Newsletter Information, undated (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Anthology, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Anthology, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Anthology, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Anthology, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Anthology Receipts, 2000-2001 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Anthology Information, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Anthology Information, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Events
  This series contains documents pertaining to events in which WIVLA played a primary role. The material may include correspondence, programs, and invitations for the stated events. For event photographs and other audio visual materials refer to Series 4.
  - 1st Annual Exhibition, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - 3rd Annual Exhibit and Readings, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - 3rd Annual Citizenship Week, November 2011 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - 4th Annual Exhibition, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - 15th Anniversary, 2010 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Annual Print Show and Sell, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Annual Print Show and Sell, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Annual Print Show and Sell, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Archway Readings, 1997, 2005-2006 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - “Arts & Healing”, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Art Bridge Houston, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - “Art for the Heart” Correspondence, 2003-2004 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - “Art for the Heart” Documents, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - “Art for the Heart” Public Relations, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Barnes and Noble, November 1999 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Baskets, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - “Bejeweled Gala”, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - “Body Language”, 2009 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - “Café on the Green”, October-December 1997 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Collaborative I, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Collaborative - La Colombe d’Or, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Collaborative - Crossings, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Collaborative - Flip Side, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Collaborative - Twists and Turns, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - DiverseWorks, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - ECO Fund, 2000, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - “Finding Balance”, 2011 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Friends of Women’s Studies 10th Anniversary, October 21, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - “Full Frontal View”, August 1997 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Get-to-Know Slide Show, undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Guestbook, 1995-1997 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Heights Fire Station, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - “History in Bloom”, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Holiday Gift Boutique, 1997-1998 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Juried Photofest, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - “A Little Bazaar”, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Living Archives Series, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Member’s Activities, 1997-1999 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - “Maybe a Miniature", 1999 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Mayor’s Summit for Women, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Member Retreat, August 18, 2010 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Membership Show, 1998-1999 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Museum of Printing History, 1998-1999 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Mystery Mural, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Omni Houston Hotel, 1997, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - “On-line”, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Randall’s Good Neighbor Program, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Salon and High Tea II, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - “Salon in Black &White” Correspondence, 1999-2000 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - “Salon in Black &White” Documents, 1999-2000 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - “Salon in Black &White” Master Lists, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - “Salon in Black &White” Response Cards, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Scholastic Art and Writing Awards, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Suitcase Show, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - “Sunday at the Salon” Correspondence, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - “Sunday at the Salon” Documents, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - “Sunday at the Salon” Financials, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - “Sunday at the Salon” Programs and Initiatives, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - “Sunday at the Salon” Response Cards, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Table Talk Luncheon, 1999, 2001, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - University of Houston Women’s Studies, 1997-2000 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Various Events, 1995-2001 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Visual Membership Exhibition, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Women United Conference, November 1999 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Workshops, 1997-2000 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - The Suitcase Show Poster, 2006 (Ovs box 6, Item 5)
- Multi-Media
  This series consists of photographs, negatives, slides, prints and audio visual materials. All material is organized by name of the event. Some photographs have been labeled with information provided by WIVLA.
  - Photographic Material
    - 1st Anniversary and Meeting, 1994-1995 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - 3rd Annual Exhibit and Reading, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - 10th Anniversary, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Anthology, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Anthology Zip Disk, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Bejeweled Gala, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Board Meeting, 2005-2006 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Board Retreat, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Board Retreat, May 2000 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Board Retreat, 2010 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Board Retreat, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Christmas Party, 1995-1996 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Christmas Party, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Christmas Party, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Circle of Fire, 2010 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Collaborative II: La Colombe d’Or, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Collaborative: Flip Side, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Collaborative: Bank of America, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Exhibit, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Firehouse Exhibits, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - General Meeting, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - General Meeting, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - General Meeting, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - General Meeting, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - General Meeting, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - General Meeting, 1999-2000 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - General Meeting, April 2000 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - General Meeting, May 2000 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - General Meeting, June 2000 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - General Meeting, July 2000 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - General Meeting, August 2000 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - General Meeting, September - November 2000 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - General Meeting, January 2001 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - General Meeting, February 2001 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - “Land of Odd” Photo Album, undated (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Literary Day, January 2006 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Mayor’s Summit, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Member Exhibit, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Miniature Exhibit, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Omni Houston Hotel, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Print Show, August 10, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - Readings at Brigid’s Place, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - Readings at Diedrich’s, July 2000 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Readings at Archway Gallery, February 2001 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - “Salon in Black and White”, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - “Salon in Black and White”, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - Salon Kick-off Party, July 2000 (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - “Seeds of Healing”, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - Show and Tell, February 20, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - Show and Tell Negatives, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - Slides, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 51)
    - “Suitcase Show”, February 6, 2006 (Box 4, Folder 52)
    - “Suitcase Show”, February 11, 2006 (Box 4, Folder 53)
    - Sunday at the Salon, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 54)
    - Sunday at the Salon, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - Unknown Event, undated (Box 4, Folder 56)
    - Unknown Event, undated (Box 4, Folder 57)
    - Unknown Event Prints, undated (Box 4, Folder 58)
    - Unknown Event, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Unknown Event Photo CD, 2010 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Unknown Exhibit, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Various Events, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Various Events, 2000-2001 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Various Events Photo CD, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Various Events Photo CD, 2010 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Visual Membership Exhibition, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - WARC, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Proof Sheets Unknown Exhibit, undated (Ovs box 6, Item 3)
  - Audio Visual
    - Archway Reading Cassette, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Suitcase Show Cassettes, 2006 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Suitcase Show DVD, 2006 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Various Materials
  This series contains materials that do not fit into any of the previous series. Most of the material held in this series does not pertain directly to WIVLA. Included are two pieces of art work made by members of the organization.
  - Clippings, 1997, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Document Discs, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Houston Women’s Caucus for Art, 2010 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Imprint Anthology, 2010 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Lifetime Membership Certificate, 2009 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Past Speakers Biographies, undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - “Robert’s Rules of Order”, 2009 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Various, undated (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Zip Disks, undated (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - “Belle,” Kathie Harris, undated (Ovs box 6, Item 1)
  - “Portrait of a 90’s Woman,” Sue Lorenz, undated (Ovs box 6, Item 2)
  - SeaTel Canvas Bag, undated (Ovs box 6, Item 4)
  - WIVLA Sign, undated (Ovs box 6, Item 6)